<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Papers We Love</title>
  <subtitle>A repository of academic computer science research papers and a community who loves reading them.</subtitle>
  <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/</id>
  <link href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/"/>
  <link href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-12-31T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Papers We Love</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>January Meetups</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2016/news/january-meetups/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2016/news/january-meetups/</id>
    <published>2015-12-31T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2016-01-17T01:00:33-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Joshua</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have another great line-up of meet-ups scheduled for January across a number of our chapters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bangalore 1/2&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-we-love-Bangalore/events/226944627/"&gt;Shor's Algorithm  Part&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bangalore 1/9&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-we-love-Bangalore/events/226999354/"&gt;Shor's Algorithm  Part&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bucharest 1/11&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-bucharest/events/227812124/"&gt;January Meetup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vienna 1/14&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Vienna/events/227146653/"&gt;Lisp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seattle 1/14&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Seattle/events/226850256/"&gt;: The Dataflow Model and Millwheel: Fault tolerant stream processing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bangalore 1/17&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-we-love-Bangalore/events/227450752/"&gt;Meet Dr. Shriram Krishnamurthi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saint Louis 1/18&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-in-saint-louis/events/226155838/"&gt;Magnetic Levitation &amp;amp; Guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Madrid 1/20&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Madrid/events/227538205/"&gt;Path, Trees and Flowers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;London 1/20&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-London/events/227661230/"&gt;Tom Crayford on 'An History and Evaluation of System R'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Montréal 1/20&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Montreal/events/227424625/"&gt;Better Bitmap Performance with Roaring Bitmaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winnipeg 1/20&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Winnipeg/events/227942585/"&gt;Communication in the Presence of Noise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Francisco 1/21&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/events/225730003/"&gt;Henry Robinson on "No compromises: distributed transactions with consistency.."&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seattle 1/27&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Seattle/events/227565360/"&gt;.: Scalable Atomic Visibility with RAMP Transactions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marina del Rey 1/27&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-LA/events/227508276/"&gt;Bill Berry on No Silver Bullet&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New York Chapter&lt;/strong&gt; would like to give special thanks to our Platinum sponsor &lt;a href="https://www.twosigma.com"&gt;TwoSigma&lt;/a&gt;. We would like to give additional thanks to &lt;a href="http://dev.theladders.com"&gt;The Ladders&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://engineering.tumblr.com"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and for providing food/refreshments and facilities for the January meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Papers: Christopher Meiklejohn's A Brief History of Chain Replication</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/topic/christopher-meiklejohns-a-brief-history-of-chain-replication/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/topic/christopher-meiklejohns-a-brief-history-of-chain-replication/</id>
    <published>2015-12-09T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-10T09:08:32-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Zeeshan</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetup Spotlight:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1QelqoU"&gt;http://bit.ly/1QelqoU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 10, 2015, &lt;a href="https://christophermeiklejohn.com/"&gt;Christopher Meikljohn&lt;/a&gt; is presenting at &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too"&gt;Papers We Love - San Francisco&lt;/a&gt; on the topic (and history) of &lt;strong&gt;Chain Replication&lt;/strong&gt;, a data replication technique that "promises a high throughput, linearizable, robust replication technique with minimal overhead to tolerate failures with only f+1 nodes[0]."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a look at some of the papers that will be discussed, starting with the original work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/images/cmeik_fig1.svg" alt="Figure from Chain Replication for Supporting High Throughput and Availability" /&gt;
&lt;img src="/assets/images/cmeik_fig2.svg" alt="Figure from Chain replication in theory and in practice" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The List:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/rvr/papers/osdi04.pdf"&gt;Chain Replication for Supporting High Throughput and Availability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sigops.org/sosp/sosp09/papers/andersen-sosp09.pdf"&gt;FAWN: A fast array of wimpy nodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sns.cs.princeton.edu/docs/craq-usenix09.pdf"&gt;Object storage on CRAQ: High-throughput chain replication for read-mostly workloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.snookles.com/scott/publications/erlang2010-slf.pdf"&gt;Chain replication in theory and in practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://hyperdex.org/papers/hyperdex.pdf"&gt;HyperDex: A Distributed, Searchable Key-Value Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://eurosys2013.tudos.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/paper/Almeida.pdf"&gt;ChainReaction: a Causal+ Consistent Datastore based on Chain Replication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ymsir.com/papers/sharding-socc.pdf"&gt;Leveraging sharding in the design of scalable replication protocols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chain-replication-for-supporting-high-throughput-and-availabilityhttpwwwcscornelleduhomervrpapersosdi04pdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/rvr/papers/osdi04.pdf"&gt;Chain Replication for Supporting High Throughput and Availability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Robbert van Renesse, Fred B Schneider
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2004&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the 6th Conference on Symposium on Opearting Systems Design &amp;amp; Implementation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chain replication is a new approach to coordinating clusters of fail-stop storage servers. The approach is intended for supporting large-scale storage services that exhibit high throughput and availability without sacrificing strong consistency guarantees. Besides outlining the chain replication protocols themselves, simulation experiments explore the performance characteristics of a prototype implementation. Throughput, availability, and several object-placement strategies (including schemes based on distributed hash table routing) are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="fawn-a-fast-array-of-wimpy-nodeshttpwwwsigopsorgsospsosp09papersandersen-sosp09pdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sigops.org/sosp/sosp09/papers/andersen-sosp09.pdf"&gt;FAWN: A fast array of wimpy nodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; David G. Andersen, Jason Franklin, Michael Kaminsky, Amar Phanishayee, Lawrence Tan, Vijay Vasudevan
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the ACM SIGOPS 22nd symposium on Operating systems principles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper presents a new cluster architecture for low-power data- intensive computing. FAWN couples low-power embedded CPUs to small amounts of local flash storage, and balances computation and I/O capabilities to enable efficient, massively parallel access to data. The key contributions of this paper are the principles of the FAWN architecture and the design and implementation of FAWN-KV—a consistent, replicated, highly available, and high-performance key- value storage system built on a FAWN prototype. Our design centers around purely log-structured datastores that provide the basis for high performance on flash storage, as well as for replication and consistency obtained using chain replication on a consistent hashing ring. Our evaluation demonstrates that FAWN clusters can handle roughly 350 key-value queries per Joule of energy—two orders of magnitude more than a disk-based system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="object-storage-on-craq-high-throughput-chain-replication-for-read-mostly-workloadshttpsnscsprincetonedudocscraq-usenix09pdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://sns.cs.princeton.edu/docs/craq-usenix09.pdf"&gt;Object storage on CRAQ: High-throughput chain replication for read-mostly workloads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jeff Terrace and Michael J. Freedman
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the 2009 conference on USENIX Annual technical conference - USENIX'09&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
Massive storage systems typically replicate and partition data over many potentially-faulty components to provide both reliability and scalability. Yet many commerciallydeployed systems, especially those designed for interactive use by customers, sacrifice stronger consistency properties in the desire for greater availability and higher throughput. This paper describes the design, implementation, and evaluation of CRAQ, a distributed object-storage system that challenges this inflexible tradeoff. Our basic approach, an improvement on Chain Replication, maintains strong consistency while greatly improving read throughput. By distributing load across all object replicas, CRAQ scales linearly with chain size without increasing consistency coordination. At the same time, it exposes noncommitted operations for weaker consistency guarantees when this suffices for some applications, which is especially useful under periods of high system churn. This paper explores additional design and implementation considerations for geo-replicated CRAQ storage across multiple datacenters to provide locality-optimized operations. We also discuss multi-object atomic updates and multicast optimizations for large-object updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chain-replication-in-theory-and-in-practicehttpwwwsnooklescomscottpublicationserlang2010-slfpdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.snookles.com/scott/publications/erlang2010-slf.pdf"&gt;Chain replication in theory and in practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Scott Lystig Fritchie
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the 9th ACM SIGPLAN workshop on Erlang - Erlang '10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
When implementing a distributed storage system, using an algo- rithm with a formal definition and proof is a wise idea. However, translating any algorithm into effective code can be difficult be- cause the implementation must be both correct and fast. This paper is a case study of the implementation of the chain replication protocol in a distributed key-value store calledHibari. In theory, the chain replication algorithmis quite simple and should be straightforward to implement correctly. In practice, however, there were many implementation details that had effects both profound and subtle. The Erlang community, as well as distributed systems implementors in general, can use the lessons learned with Hibari (specifically in areas of performance enhancements and failure detection) to avoid many dangers that lurk at the interface between theory and real-world computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="hyperdex-a-distributed-searchable-key-value-storehttphyperdexorgpapershyperdexpdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://hyperdex.org/papers/hyperdex.pdf"&gt;HyperDex: A Distributed, Searchable Key-Value Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Robert Escriva, Bernard Wong, Emin Gün Sirer
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Computer Communication Review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
Distributed key-value stores are now a standard component of high-performance web services and cloud computing applications. While key-value stores offer significant performance and scalability advantages compared to traditional databases, they achieve these properties through a restricted API that limits object retrieval an object can only be retrieved by the (primary and only) key under which it was inserted. This paper presents HyperDex, a novel distributed key-value store that provides a unique search primitive that enables queries on secondary attributes. The key insight behind HyperDex is the concept of hyperspace hashing in which objects with multiple attributes are mapped into a multidimensional hyperspace. This mapping leads to efficient implementations not only for retrieval by primary key, but also for partially-specified secondary attribute searches and range queries. A novel chaining protocol enables the system to achieve strong consistency, maintain availability and guarantee fault tolerance. An evaluation of the full system shows that HyperDex is 12-13x faster than Cassandra and MongoDB for finding partially specified objects. Additionally, HyperDex achieves 2-4x higher throughput for get/put operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="chainreaction-a-causal-consistent-datastore-based-on-chain-replicationhttpeurosys2013tudosorgwp-contentuploads2013paperalmeidapdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://eurosys2013.tudos.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/paper/Almeida.pdf"&gt;ChainReaction: a Causal+ Consistent Datastore based on Chain Replication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sérgio Almeida, João Leitão, Luís Rodrigues
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of The European Professional Society on Computer Systems (EuroSys)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
This paper proposes a Geo-distributed key-value datastore, named ChainReaction, that offers causal+ consistency, with high performance, fault-tolerance, and scalability. ChainReaction enforces causal+ consistency which is stronger than eventual consistency by leveraging on a new variant of chain replication.We have experimentally evaluated the benefits of our approach by running the Yahoo! Cloud Serving Benchmark. Experimental results show that ChainReaction has better performance in read intensive workloads while offering competitive performance for other workloads. Also we show that our solution requires less metadata when compared with previous work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id="leveraging-sharding-in-the-design-of-scalable-replication-protocolshttpwwwymsircompaperssharding-soccpdf"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ymsir.com/papers/sharding-socc.pdf"&gt;Leveraging sharding in the design of scalable replication protocols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hussam Abu-Libdeh, Robbert van Renesse, Ymir Vigfusson
&lt;strong&gt;Year:&lt;/strong&gt; 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published-in:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the 4th annual Symposium on Cloud Computing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
Most if not all datacenter services use sharding and repli- cation for scalability and reliability. Shards are more-or- less independent of one another and individually repli- cated. In this paper, we challenge this design philosophy and present a replication protocol where the shards inter- act with one another: A protocol running within shards ensures linearizable consistency, while the shards inter- act in order to improve availability.We provide a specifi- cation for the protocol, prove its safety, analyze its live- ness and availability properties, and evaluate a working implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id="other-references"&gt;Other References&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Seattle/"&gt;Papers We Love - Seattle&lt;/a&gt;'s David Murray on Chain Replication for Supporting High Throughput and Availability - &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nEbD-qutsKo"&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt; : &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1ITPeQ8"&gt;Meetup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nuprl.org/FDLcontentAUXdocs/ChainRepl/"&gt;Formalizing the Chain Replication Protocol&lt;/a&gt; -
This book collects materials used in the formalization of an important distributed algorithm, by Schneider and van Renesse, called Chain Replication. The chain replication algorithm provides a fault-tolerant distributed storage system and guarantees a strong consistency property. The material here includes: the original Schneider and van Renesse paper; a summary of the formalization method, by Bickford &amp;amp; Guaspari; a detailed outline of the formalization by Bickford; and a Nuprl library providing a formal account based on the Logic of Events described by Bickford and Constable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.mendeley.com/groups/7644501/papers-we-love/papers/added/0/tag/chain_replication/"&gt;Mendeley Tag for &lt;em&gt;cmjchainreplication&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - More resources and information about the papers mentioned here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[0] &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/events/224178870/"&gt;http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/events/224178870/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>December Meetups</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/news/december-meetups/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/news/december-meetups/</id>
    <published>2015-11-30T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-31T19:00:32-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Joshua</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have another great line-up of meet-ups scheduled for December across a number of our chapters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vienna 12/1&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Vienna/events/226580589/"&gt;Out of the Tar Pit (part )&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Madrid 12/2&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Madrid/events/226986420/"&gt;Diff and Blame: an intuitive overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seattle 12/10&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Seattle/events/226493450/"&gt;: A Critique of the CAP Theorem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Francisco 12/10&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/events/224178870/"&gt;Nathan Taylor on OS scalability &amp;amp; Chris Meiklejohn on Chain Replication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bangalore 12/12&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-we-love-Bangalore/events/226454656/"&gt;Let's Shazaam with Arpit Mohan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bucharest 12/15&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-bucharest/events/226723178/"&gt;December Meetup&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New York Chapter&lt;/strong&gt; would like to give special thanks to our Platinum sponsor &lt;a href="https://www.twosigma.com"&gt;TwoSigma&lt;/a&gt;. We would like to give additional thanks to &lt;a href="http://dev.theladders.com"&gt;The Ladders&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://engineering.tumblr.com"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and for providing food/refreshments and facilities for the December meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tom Santero on Leslie Lamport's Buridan’s Principle</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/video/tom-santero-buridans-principle/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/video/tom-santero-buridans-principle/</id>
    <published>2015-11-18T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2015-12-10T09:08:32-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Zeeshan</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe class="video" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dVkSJ0QWzXA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-york---november-19-2015"&gt;New York - November 19, 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tom Santero&lt;/strong&gt; on Leslie Lamport's Buridan’s Principle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetup:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1NTZy22"&gt;http://bit.ly/1NTZy22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/21MPCvo"&gt;http://bit.ly/21MPCvo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1OOfVfi"&gt;http://bit.ly/1OOfVfi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1NFtzAB"&gt;http://bit.ly/1NFtzAB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1984 Leslie Lamport began to observe the glitch problem [&lt;a href="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/lamport/pubs/glitch.pdf"&gt;0&lt;/a&gt;] occurs in everyday life. Realizing this phenomenon had not been discussed by psychologists of the day, he set out to describe his observations using the classical formalization of Buridan's ass. Lamport initially failed to have this paper published in various scientific journals, being rejected on grounds of superficiality. It wasn't until 2011, when a reader suggested he resubmit to Foundations of Physics, that the paper was eventually published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those familiar with the works of Lamport know him as a logician, his life's work has pushed forward the state of the art in areas of mutual exclusion and distributed systems probably more than any other, and so reading Buridan's Principle might strike us as a bit odd, or even obscure. We're in unfamiliar territory with Lamport. Nonetheless, in this paper, Lamport's casual observations lead him to bridge the gap between the humanities and the sciences, providing us readers with what appears to be a universal law of nature: Buridan's Principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[0] &lt;a href="http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/lamport/pubs/glitch.pdf"&gt;http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/lamport/pubs/glitch.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Santero (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tsantero"&gt;@tsantero&lt;/a&gt;) is a Software Engineer at Helium Systems, writing Haskell and Erlang to connect things to the internet. Previously, Tom worked at the New York Times on Search infrastructure, and before that he ran evangelism at Basho Technologies. A native New Yorker, Tom recently defected to Fort Collins, CO, where he lives with his two cats nearby an obnoxiously loud freight train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.twosigma.com/"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/TwoSigma_RGB.jpg" alt="TwoSigma" title="TwoSigma - Platinum Sponsor of Papers We Love NYC" style="width: 200px; margin: 0 1em 0 0;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style="flex: 1;"&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New York Chapter&lt;/strong&gt; would like to thank &lt;a href="http://www.twosigma.com"&gt;TwoSigma&lt;/a&gt; for helping to make this meetup possible.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>November Meetups</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/news/november-meetups/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/news/november-meetups/</id>
    <published>2015-10-31T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-30T20:44:18-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Joshua</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have another great line-up of meet-ups scheduled for November across a number of our chapters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toronto 11/4&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Toronto/events/226167802/"&gt;Raveesh Nagpal on An Error Model for Pointing Based on Fitts’ Law&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vienna 11/5&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Vienna/events/225544086/"&gt;Out of the Tar Pit (part )&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bangalore 11/7&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-we-love-Bangalore/events/225439494/"&gt;A Geocoding Algorithm Based On A Comparative Study with Shravanthi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seattle 11/12&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Seattle/events/225811209/"&gt;: Survivable Key Compromise in Software Update Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saint Louis 11/16&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-in-saint-louis/events/226155831/"&gt;Differential Expression Analysis: Finding Genes that Matter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;London 11/18&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-London/events/226303374/"&gt;Camilla MontonenSupport Vector Machines and Kernels for Computational Biology.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New York 11/19&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love/events/226193314/"&gt;Tom Santero on Leslie Lamport's Buridan’s Principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Francisco 11/19&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/papers-we-love-too/events/224178862/"&gt;Gareth Morgan on The Rendering Equation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Munich 11/24&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Munich/events/224164184/"&gt;Probabilistic Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Montréal 11/25&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Montreal/events/225581672/"&gt;"A Survey of Monte Carlo Tree Search Methods"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Winnipeg 11/25&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/Papers-We-Love-Winnipeg/events/226080050/"&gt;Do Artifacts Have Politics?&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New York Chapter&lt;/strong&gt; would like to give special thanks to our Platinum sponsor &lt;a href="https://www.twosigma.com"&gt;TwoSigma&lt;/a&gt;. We would like to give additional thanks to &lt;a href="http://dev.theladders.com"&gt;The Ladders&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://engineering.tumblr.com"&gt;Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; and for providing food/refreshments and facilities for the November meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tomas Petricek on The Against Method</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/video/tomas-petricek-against-the-method/"/>
    <id>http://papers-we-love.github.io/2015/video/tomas-petricek-against-the-method/</id>
    <published>2015-10-04T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2015-10-14T19:59:50-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Darren</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;iframe class="video" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jzD1O_gastA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="new-york---october-5-2015"&gt;New York - October 5, 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tomas Petricek&lt;/strong&gt; on The Against Method&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meetup:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1VOG3eT"&gt;http://bit.ly/1VOG3eT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1Lhaxfo"&gt;http://bit.ly/1Lhaxfo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1G1QPHK"&gt;http://bit.ly/1G1QPHK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1jzWz0J"&gt;http://bit.ly/1jzWz0J&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is computer science research done? What we take for granted and what we question? And how do theories in computer science tell us something about the real world? Those are some of the questions that may inspire computer scientist like me (and you!) to look into philosophy of science. I’ll present the work of one of the more extreme (and interesting!) philosophers of science, Paul Feyerabend. In “Against Method”, Feyerabend looks at the history of science and finds that there is no fixed scientific methodology and the only methodology that can encompass the rich history is ‘anything goes’. We see (not only computer) science as a perfect methodology for building correct knowledge, but is this really the case? To quote Feyerabend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Science is much more 'sloppy' and 'irrational' than its methodological image."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be mostly talking about Paul Feyerabend’s “Against Method”, but as a computer scientist myself, I’ll insert a number of examples based on my experience with theoretical programming language research. I hope to convince you that looking at philosophy of science is very much worthwhile if we want to better understand what we do and how we do it as computer scientists!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomas Petricek (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tomaspetricek"&gt;@tomaspetricek&lt;/a&gt;) recently submitted his PhD thesis at University of Cambridge on context-aware programming languages. He is active in the functional programming community, contributes to various F# open-source libraries, writes and talks about F# and offers trainings and consulting at fsharpWorks. When he isn’t writing equations or code, he enjoys reading philosophy of science books and occasionally publishes an essay combining philosophy and computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; align-items: center;"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.twosigma.com/"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/TwoSigma_RGB.jpg" alt="TwoSigma" title="TwoSigma - Platinum Sponsor of Papers We Love NYC" style="width: 200px; margin: 0 1em 0 0;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span style="flex: 1;"&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;New York Chapter&lt;/strong&gt; would like to thank &lt;a href="http://www.twosigma.com"&gt;TwoSigma&lt;/a&gt; for helping to make this meetup possible.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
